Dorothy Kenyon Papers, 1850-1998
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
"United Nations, Freedom of Information," notes for speech before International Council of Women 9/47 Box 20
"Woman's Eye View [of the UN]," notes for speech for Woman's Action Committee 10/47 Box 20
"Make a Will," speech at the League of Business and Professional Women 10/47 Box 20
Untitled speech ["Women's Eye View--Visit to UN with Florence Allen"] for College Women's Club of Montclair 10/47 Box 20
"Women and the United Nations" 1947 Box 20
"Role of Women in the World Today," speech for unidentified occasion 1947 Box 20
"International Women's Day," speech for Pioneer Women's Organization 1947 Box 20
"Woman as a Force in History," notes for speech for unidentified occasion 1947 Box 20
"We and the United Nations" 3/48 Box 21
Untitled remarks ["It is a familiar slip of the tongue to say United States when one means United Nations] from panel discussion "Shifting Status of Women" at Women's Bureau Conference 2/48 Box 21
"Women and the United Nations," notes for speech for American Association of University Women, Poughkeepsie 3/48 Box 21
"International Marriages," speech before National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship 3/48 Box 21
"Releasing Women's Potentialities," speech before The Round Table Club 3/48 Box 21
"Participation of Women," notes for speech before the Zonta Club of Patterson 3/48 Box 21
"Dr. Catharine McFarlane," speech for The Woman's Medical College of Pennsylvania 4/48 Box 21
"Women and the United Nations," speech given before Soroptimists Club of Detroit 4/48 Box 21
"The Responsibility of American Women," speech before Pennsylvania Federation of Women's Clubs Convention 5/48 Box 21
"Women's Problems as Reviewed by the U.N.," speech before Massachusetts Division of the American Association of University Women" 5/48 Box 21
"Remaining Discriminations in Laws Affecting Women," notes for speech before Connecticut CSA-Women's Division 5/48 Box 21
"The Awakening of Women," speech delivered at the Women's Rights Centennial, Seneca Falls, NY 7/48 Box 21
"Women and the UN 7/48 Box 21
"Some Problems in the Field of Nationality of Married Women," speech delivered before the International Bar Association meeting 7/48 Box 21
"The Awakening of Women Fall 1948 Box 21
"Commission on the Status of Women Broadcast," remarks for radio broadcast 9/48 Box 21
Untitled speech about Soviet women 12/48 Box 21
"Responsibility of American Women," speech delivered on unidentified occasion 1948 Box 21
"The College Woman in Life," notes for speech delivered at Goucher College 1/49 Box 21
"The Place of Women in the Modern World," keynote address at Oberlin Symposium on Occupations for Women 2/49 Box 21
"Equality and Freedom" 3/49 Box 21
Untitled transcript of questions posed to DK for CBS Radio broadcast about women's rights 6/49 Box 21
"Crossing New Frontiers" 6/49 Box 21
"Crossing New Frontiers," excerpts from address delivered at 1949 Biennial Convention of American Association of University Women 1949 Box 21
Untitled remarks ["Frustration--nothing to do with career..."] for NBC "Theater of the Mind" broadcast about career women: manuscript and typewritten script 8/49 Box 21
"Women and the United Nations," notes for speech at Chautauqua 8/49 Box 21
Proposed questions for professional women's panel including DK at Women's American Institute of Banking Forum Dinner 11/49 Box 21
Untitled remarks taken from Seneca Falls speech ["that women were not fungible goods, i.e. identical with men as grains of sand..."] 1949 Box 21
Untitled remarks about women's changing status ["A plague on both your houses!"] late 1940s Box 19
"Tide Over Harvard" 1/50 Box 21
"Women and Other People," speech delivered to League of Business and Professional Women, Brooklyn 2/50 Box 21
"Case (By One of Them) For Women Lawyers" 2/50 Box 21
"The Meaning of Equality," speech delivered to American Civil Liberties Union 2/50 Box 21
Untitled speech ["King Solomon..."] delivered to NYU Women's Law Class 6/50 Box 21
"What Women Have Done," speech delivered at Barnard Forum 11/51 Box 21
Notes for untitled speech ["First job as lawyer..."] delivered to Women's University Club Midcentury Conference on Careers for Women 4/51 Box 21
Notes for untitled speech ["Brief introduction. Document to be circulated later"] delivered to Commission on the Status of Women 5/51 Box 21
"Education for Women" 1951 Box 21
"Educated Women and Controversial Issues" 2/51 Box 21
"Women's Freedom in Our New World," notes for speech delivered at Providence YWCA 4/51 Box 21
"Beirut--East and West Women Meet" 4/51 Box 21
"Women in World Affairs," speech delivered at unidentified occasion 5/51 Box 21
"Women Jurors--1951," speech delivered at Women's City Club 1951 Box 21
"Alimony" 1951 Box 21
"Reflections on the Status of Women," speech delivered on unidentified occasion 4/53 Box 21
"Equal Rights for Women" 1953 Box 21
"Equal Rights for Women" 6/54 Box 22
"ACLU--Women's Rights," notes for speech given on unidentified occasion circa 1954 Box 22
"The Role of Women in the World Today," speech delivered at New York Society for Ethical Culture 1/55 Box 22
"Restatement of ACLU Position in Favor of Women's Rights" 6/55 Box 22
Untitled speech ["We are 40 years old--a ripe age..."] for Women's City Club 11/55 Box 22
"Women in Political Life," speech delivered to Sisterhood of Temple B'nai Sholom and Sisterhood of Central Synagogue 12/55 Box 22
"What Life to Choose 4/56 Box 22
"Human Rights of Women All Over the World," speech delivered to Women's Auxiliary of International Typographical Union 8/57 Box 22
"The Legal Concept of Equality," speech delivered at Albert Einstein College of Medicine 4/59 Box 22
"Sophia Smith Collection," notes and speech delivered to Smith College Friends of the Smith College Library 4/59 Box 22
Untitled speech ["I am happy to have been chosen to tell you something tonight about those saintly old ladies who founded our club..."] delivered to charter members of the Women's City Club 5/59 Box 22
"Lawyer and Judge," article in unidentified YWCA publication 5/59 Box 22
"A Second Look at Women's Education," notes for panel discussion at Women's University Club Birthday Party 10/59 Box 22
"Winifred Pitkin--Life," speech delivered to Business and Professional Women's League of Rockland County 4/60 Box 22
"Jane Addams--Champion of Humanity," speech delivered at Women's International League for Peace and Freedom Centennial Conference 10/60 Box 22
"The Status of Women--The Family Unit," speech delivered to Parents Without Partners 1/62 Box 22
Testimony of DK on Equal Pay Bills before Congressional Committee on Education and Labor 4/62 Box 22
"Women's Opportunities," speech delivered at Baldwin School on its 75th Anniversary 10/63 Box 23
Untitled partial transcript of radio broadcast panel on courtship, marriage, divorce 5/64 Box 23
"Jane Crow and Lily-White Males 1/66 Box 23
"Discriminations Against Women 6/66 Box 23
"The Educated Woman Never Had it so Good," speech delivered to Nyack branch of AAUW and League of Women Voters 12/66 Box 23
"Women of the USA, Awake!" 3/67 Box 23
"Divorce Law," speech delivered at Women's City Club 4/68 Box 23
"Men and Women--Boredom, Violence and Political Power" circa 1960 Box 22
Untitled speech introducing Carmel Carrington Marr at Women's City Club Report on Women's Rights 6/70 Box 23
Untitled remarks made in television interview at women's liberation demonstration at Statue of Liberty 8/70 Box 23
Transcript of testimony to City of New York Commission on Human Rights 9/70 Box 23
"The Equal Rights Amendment" 12/70 Box 23
"Women's Liberation--Equal Rights Amendment" circa 1970 Box 23
"Reflections on the World," delivered by DK at Women's City Club party in DK's honor 5/71 Box 23
"Women's Liberation 1971 Box 23
"Invisible Non-People, Victims of the Common Law--Why?" 8/71 Box 23
"Women's Place is in the Home, Men and Women--Boredom, Violence and Political Power, Conclusion" 1971 Box 23
"Women and the Law" n.d. Box 23
"Marriage--a business or a spiritual relationship" n.d. Box 23
"Husband and Wife" n.d. Box 23
"Wife's Right of Personality" n.d. Box 23
"Women and Crime" n.d. Box 23
Untitled manuscript about the Society for the Preservation of Women's Archives, n.d. n.d. Box 23
"Women's Personal Rights as Affected by Marriage" n.d. Box 23
"Women in the Modern World" n.d. Box 23
"Marriage and the Law" n.d. Box 23
"Women are Human Beings" n.d. Box 23
"Equality and Freedom" n.d. Box 23
"Commission on the Status of Women Broadcast" n.d. Box 23
"Women's Place is in the Home?" n.d. Box 23
"The Equal Rights Amendment--Do Women Have Equality" n.d. Box 23
"Next Steps in the Emancipation of Women An Equal Rights Amendment?" n.d. Box 23
Untitled speech about women's status internationally n.d. Box 23
"Laws Concerning Family Support," outline for speech n.d. Box 23
"Woman's Rights and Powers As Affected by Marriage," outline for speech n.d. Box 23
Untitled fragment about women and work ["Thus women and with them the entire race are debased] n.d. Box 23
Untitled fragment about women and work [so there is nothing surprising perhaps in the fact that these two gentleman...] n.d. Box 23
World War II and American foreign policy
Notes about Italian women and fascism 1937 Box 19
Notes about situation in Europe ["Refugees everywhere"] for speech delivered at Spanish Refugee Mass Meeting 3/38 Box 19
Untitled remarks from the Peace Parade 8/38 Box 19
"The Charter Nobody Knows," remarks for radio broadcast 10/38 Box 19
Untitled remarks ["When I first heard the word subversive..."] for radio broadcast 10/38 Box 19
"With Malice Toward None," remarks delivered to Chelsea Council 8/39 Box 19
"War Profiteering on Food" 10/39 Box 19
"New World," speech at Connecticut (?) College 10/38 Box 19
"The Threat to Women in the New European Alignment and What Geneva is Doing to Help," remarks to New York Business and Professional Women 11/38 Box 19
Untitled remarks about Spain 11/38 Box 19
Untitled remarks about Spanish Embargo 11/38 Box 19
"Justice Under Nazi-ism," remarks to Anti-Nazi Organization 1/39 Box 19
"The Embargo," remarks for radio broadcast 2/39 Box 19
Untitled speech for Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born 3/39 Box 19
Untitled remarks to West End Association 3/39 Box 19
Untitled remarks to Europe Collegiate Club 5/39 Box 19
Untitled notes ["Defend America and the Allies..."] 2/40 Box 19
"United States of Europe," speech about conflicts among European nations delivered to New Era Club 1940 Box 19
Untitled remarks ["Hitler's hordes are not attacking the British and French alone..."] for Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies 6/40 Box 19
"Good Americans--How to Be One!" speech at Manhattan Beach 7/40 Box 19
"Civil Liberties in War Time," speech for Humanity Guild 7/40 Box 19
"Good Americans--How to Be One" speech for World's Fair 9/40 Box 19
Untitled remarks ["It is splendid news..."] 9/40 Box 19
"Three Point Program," article about free speech and Fifth Columnists 11/40 Box 19
"European Women Under Fascism," speech for Woman's Centennial Congress 11/40 Box 19
"Women in Defense," speech for Soroptimists 1/41 Box 20
Untitled notes for speech on women in the military ["All existing socieities of women cooperating..."] 1/41 Box 20
Untitled remarks [In these dangerous days when the Nazis] 2/41 Box 20
Untitled notes ["High hopes--March 1938"] for speech and Smith Club of Queens 1938 Box 19
"Economic Defense of the Americas," speech for Committee on Inter-American Cooperation 3/41 Box 20
"Can Democracy Survive?" speech for White Plains ACLU 3/41 Box 20
Untitled notes for remarks at Soroptimists Club program "Woman's Place in the National Defense" 4/41 Box 20
"Why I am an Enemy of Nazism" 6/41 Box 20
Untitled notes ["Y.W. in Europe..."] for speech at YWCA 10/41 Box 20
"The New World Comes of Age," editorial for Chelsean 1/42 Box 20
Untitled notes ["One of those cases where each is convinced..."] for radio broadcast 2/42 Box 20
Untitled remarks ["Even among citizens reasonable classifications are appropriate..."] re 3/42 Box 20
"Why Talk Now of Post-war Problems?" questions for discussion for radio broadcast 3/42 Box 20
Untitled notes ["Walling--Federal Wages and hours..."] for remarks at 42nd Annual meeting of National Consumers League to discuss "Our Industrial Army 3/42 Box 20
"Women in the War and After," speech for the Council of Women 4/42 Box 20
Untitled speech ["Amy Lowell Says war is a pattern..."] for Sweet Briar College 4/42 Box 20
"National Needs and Resources," in The Institute in Review 4/42 Box 20
"American Flag," speech for American Labor Party 5/42 Box 20
"Women and the World Order," speech given at Smith College 6/42 Box 20
Untitled notes ["good government--exciting from local to international..."] 7/42 Box 20
"The Voice of Freedom," speech at WMCA Freedom House 9/42 Box 20
"Winning the War and Peace," notes for remarks to League of Women Voters 10/42 Box 20
"Trade Barriers Between States," remarks for radio broadcast 11/42 Box 20
"Women Doctors in the Army," speech delivered to AMWA 12/42 Box 20
Untitled speech for Women in War Congress at Girls Commercial High School 12/42 Box 20
Untitled article for The Cooperative Crier about government during wartime 1942 Box 20
"England Leads the Way," speech for Women's City Club 2/43 Box 20
Untitled notes ["I call for Color Guard..."] for speech for The Anti-Defamation League 2/43 Box 20
"Staff of the World Organization," roundtable discussion on U.N. 3/43 Box 20
Untitled notes ["Shifting times--may shift for women too"] for speech 4/43 Box 20
"Compulsory Registration of Women," remarks for radio broadcast 4/43 Box 20
"World After the War," notes for speech at Women's City Club of NY 5/43 Box 20
"Cooperatives 9/43 Box 20
"Should Women be Drafted?" in The American Forum of the Air 10/43 Box 20
"Women's Action Committee for Victory and Lasting Peace," remarks at NYT Conference 10/43 Box 20
"An International Bill of Rights," speech at Free World Conference 10/43 Box 20
"Replacement of Men by Women and Equal Pay," for the Industrial Bulletin 1/44 Box 20
Untitled speech ["War does strange things..."] at Labor Standards Conference 2/44 Box 20
"Looking Forward," introductory remarks by DK at Annual Meeting of Women's Action Committee for Victory and Lasting Peace 5/44 Box 20
"Should Immigration Restrictions be Stiffened After the War" 2/45 Box 20
Untitled speech ["Life in international world--Smith Students..."] for Smith College 4/47 Box 20
Notes for Untitled speech ["San Francisco--fundamental freedoms, without distinction to race, sex, language, religion"] for York, PA Soroptimists 4/47 Box 20
Notes for untitled speech ["Charter--human rights"] for Northfield School 4/47 Box 20
"The World--Now or Never," speech given in Trenton, NJ 4/47 Box 20
Untitled speech ["San Francisco--the delicate flower is from stormy days in London..."] for American Association of University Women 5/47 Box 20
"U.S. Foreign Policy," notes for speech delivered before Westchester Americans for Democratic Action 3/51 Box 21
Untitled speech about Vietnam policy and the attitude toward President Johnson 9/68 Box 23
Miscellaneous
"The Five Year Plan in the Flesh," for speech delivered at Cosmopolitan Club 4/37 Box 19
Untitled notes for speech about Hillside Hospital 2/40 Box 19
Untitled notes for remarks at Research Council on the Problems of Alcohol 5/40 Box 19
Untitled remarks ["In these days of storm and turmoil..."] for speech at Salisbury Connecticut Bicentennial 8/41 Box 20
Untitled remarks for radio broadcast ["Casting out the devils was an ancient form of healing..."] 1942 Box 20
Untitled notes ["Police Department Boys Band"] for remarks 2/43 Box 20
"Rochdale Centennial," notes for speech at Free World Association 12/43 Box 20
Untitled speech ["Strawberry festival--they agree with me..."], given in Far Rockaway, NY 5/45 Box 20
Untitled remarks about the Girl Scouts of Greater New York for radio broadcast 10/48 Box 21
Untitled remarks about Girl Scouts for radio broadcast 12/49 Box 21
"The State Division and the New By-Laws," remarks at AAUW meeting 6/50 Box 21
"Speech Making," article for Junior League Magazine 11/51 Box 21
Untitled remarks about Roosevelt Day Dinner delivered to Americans for Democratic Action-West Side Branch 12/52 Box 21
"City Report," report delivered at ADA National Board Mtg 1/55 Box 22
Notes for untitled remarks about traffic and parking for radio broadcast 12/55 Box 22
Untitled speech delivered to Women's City Club 10/62 Box 22
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL (1888-1980), 2.8 linear feet
  This series includes a variety of material by and about Dorothy Kenyon that documents her personal history, her professional activities, and her wide-ranging accomplishments. It is arranged in the following subseries: Writings about Kenyon, Interviews, Tributes and testimonials, Education, Awards, Honorary degrees, Memberships, Legal documents, Financial documents, Contacts, Calendars, Professional credentials, Funeral records, and Memorabilia. The bulk of the items in this series date from 1920-71. Memorabilia contains a significant amount of material from Kenyon's infancy and childhood, including a meticulously detailed baby book kept by her father, William Stanton Kenyon. Writings about Kenyon includes biographical and autobiographical material, resumes, newspaper clippings and an unpublished scholarly article. The material assembled by Kenyon's sister-in-law and prospective biographer Mildred Adams Kenyon consists of approximately 1 linear foot containing research notes, correspondence, reminiscences, a few photographs, and a complete draft of Mildred Kenyon's unpublished book. This material is particularly rich as it contains a great deal of information about Dorothy Kenyon's childhood and personal life that is not evident in the documents she herself saved. This subseries spans the years from 1924 until 1980 when Mildred Adams Kenyon died. See also oral history tapes in SERIES IX. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL.
- SERIES II. FAMILY (1850-1998), 1.6 linear feet
  This series consists primarily of correspondence but it also contains financial records, keepsakes, legal documents, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, and writings generated by or about various members of Kenyon's extended family between 1850 and 1998. The series is divided into two subseries: Individuals and Special events. Individuals is arranged alphabetically with material about miscellaneous family members filed at the end of the subseries. Each person's file contains various types of material by or about them. These papers document individuals' lives but they also reveal a great deal about interpersonal relationships, early 20th-century upper-middle-class child-rearing practices, and Kenyon family history. Most of the keepsakes, financial documents, memorabilia and writings in this series originated with Kenyon's father William Houston Kenyon. Special events includes MATERIAL related to William Stanton Kenyon's wedding to his second wife Lestra Kinney Kenyon in 1909, and the multi-generational Kenyon family railroad trip to the Canadian Rockies in 1969. These are also arranged alphabetically and contain material by or about various members of the Kenyon family. See also oral history tapes in SERIES IX. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL, and SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS.
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE (1917-1971), 3.3 linear feet
  This series contains both personal and professional correspondence. Family correspondence can be found in SERIES II. FAMILY. Correspondence related to specific political appointments, organization work or other activities is filed in the appropriate series. This series is arranged in three subseries: General, Friends and associates, and Letters to the editor. General correspondence includes incoming and outgoing letters dating from 1918 to 1972, with the vast majority of the letters generated between 1949 and 1972. This subseries consists of routine personal, professional and political correspondence arranged chronologically. Typical correspondence included here are personal letters congratulating Kenyon on her various achievements, fundraising requests, holiday greetings, invitations, public response mail, RSVPs, and thank you notes. Friends and associates dates from 1917 to 1971 and contains both personal and professional correspondence arranged alphabetically. It includes such significant signatories as Hubert Humphrey, Fiorello LaGuardia, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Harry Truman, among many others, whose letters demonstrate Kenyon's political prominence during the 1930s-60s. This subseries also includes candid and revealing correspondence with some of Kenyon's most intimate associates such as Walcott Pitkin, Gertrude Besse King, Elihu Root, and L. Valentine Pulsifer. Kenyon's Letters to the editor date from 1948-1971 and are arranged chronologically. They address many and varied topics including civil liberties, civil rights, U.S. foreign policy, New York City and international politics, integration, the legal system, and women's rights.
- SERIES IV. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS (1925-1972), 3.75 linear feet
  Dorothy Kenyon was a prolific writer and a much sought-after speaker. This series contains published articles, unpublished drafts, speech notes and texts, and related correspondence and publicity. It is arranged in five subseries: Correspondence, Articles and addresses, Book reviews, Encyclopedia entries, and Book-length manuscripts, with each of these arranged chronologically. Correspondence includes primarily writing and speaking invitations and negotiations regarding honoraria and travel arrangements dating from 1946-1970. Articles and addresses comprises the largest category in this series. They date from 1925-71, are arranged chronologically, and include notes, drafts, and final versions of articles and speeches with related publicity enclosed. In keeping with her broad involvement in social justice activities, Kenyon wrote and spoke about a large number of subjects including anti-communism, civil liberties, education, internationalism, politics, racism, and women's rights, among many others. See the >Appendix for a listing of articles and addresses by subject.
- SERIES V. LEGAL PRACTICE (1936-1969), 1.25 linear feet
  This series contains material that relates directly to Kenyon's legal career. It does not include any client or case files; Houston and Mildred Kenyon, who facilitated the transfer of Kenyon's papers to the Sophia Smith Collection, regarded that material as strictly private. The series is arranged in four subseries: Clients and contacts, Cases, Judicial files, and Research files. Clients and contacts contains lists of Kenyon's clients, lists of the documents and material she held in safekeeping for some of those clients, and contact information for both clients and professional associates. Cases includes appeals, briefs, and motions for cases in which Kenyon was directly involved in her private practice as well as for the American Civil Liberties Union and the New York City Bar Association. These are arranged by case and in chronological order. Judicial files contains a small amount of material Kenyon saved from her short tenure as a municipal judge including a collection of jury charges, an outline of the judge's role during a trial, and one opinion Kenyon rendered as a judge. Research files consists of legal briefs, memoranda, petitions, and printed records of cases in which Kenyon was interested, but not directly involved. These are arranged chronologically.
- SERIES VI. ACTIVITIES AND ORGANIZATIONS (1923-1971), 15.0 linear feet